Hello, I'm your host David Bernard and
with me today RevenueCat CEO Jacob
Eiding. Our guest today is Charlie
Cheever, the co-founder and CEO of Expo,
the easiest way to create native apps
and websites that run everywhere using
React. On the podcast we talk with
Charlie about why React Native has
become the default for VC funded apps.
How AI is accelerating development
cycles.
And why speed of iteration matters more
than programming language.
Hey Charlie, thanks so much for joining
us on the podcast. Hey, thanks for
having me. It's awesome to be here.
And Jacob, nice to have you on as well
today. Excited to talk about I think one
of the a dev tool I've been aware for a
long time has also become suddenly super
super relevant in 2025. So yeah, Expo.
Yeah, Charlie, so there's a lot of
reasons I wanted to have you on the
podcast, but the main one kind of Jacob
alluded to. As CEO of Expo, you're
seeing a lot of things happen these days
with new people getting into to
programming with React specifically
becoming more and more popular, more and
more used, kind of the the default for a
lot of companies to build on. So I don't
want to we just kick things off with
kind of a high-level overview. I think a
lot of folks listening won't be
developers themselves, so they might not
kind of understand what React Native is
and we can talk about that and then as
well as like how Expo works with that.
So yeah, tell us a little bit about
React. Yeah, so React is this JavaScript
framework that was invented
gosh, you know, over a decade ago by a
guy named Jordan Walke at Facebook to
build complicated UIs in a way that you
could reason about and generate
consistently. The core idea is that it's
sort of component-based, so like the way
a human being would break down a product
or a UI, it winds up pretty much with
that. You know, you'd say like, "Oh,
here's my pricing component and within
that I have, you know, the dollars
component, the cents component" or
something like that. But then the the
real magic to it is that you represent
state as sort of like you have this
abstract state of the world and then the
UI is always sort of being re-rendered
to update to to represent whatever the
current state of the world is. And so if
you remember like older websites, a lot
of times you would have, you know, you
might click a button to say follow
somebody and
it would update correctly where you
clicked, but then things sort of would
look incorrect in other parts of the
screen or there would just sort of be
these inconsistencies with that. And as
a general rule when you use React, all
of this stuff sort of magically falls
into place because you know, this stuff
happens. Actually, this sort of idea, I
believe, sort of came from
the way that
video games have come to work. So if you
think about like really old video games,
like, you know, a snake is moving across
the screen on a really low-res monitor.
And so the way that the snake moves is
that you you draw one more pixel on the
right for the head to move a little one
step further and you erase one pixel on
the far left for the tail to kind of
shimmy forward. It's simple enough that
you can actually just like manipulate
pixels directly to kind of change things
how you want them to be. But then if you
imagine, you know, sort of a a modern
video game or anything once you get into
the era of 3D, it's kind of like think
about like Call of Duty and like trying
to figure out what any given pixel on
the screen is just crazy to to figure
out how to do that. And so the way that
the people end up doing it is basically
having some sort of representation
what's going on in the world and then a
system that sort of figures out, "Okay,
here's this 3D model and it's made up of
all these triangles, so we're going to
draw this here." And then, you know,
everything gets sort of re-rendered
every frame because of that. And so
React is sort of that for UIs for
applications. And so
it's become by far the most popular way
to build websites these days. And
there's still a lot of older code out
there that's using like jQuery and
Angular is still pretty big, but like
almost everything new that's done by,
you know, reasonable people is is done
using React.
Or run your cat.com, app.runyourcat.com,
reasonable people.
Yeah. All this AI development is even
further accelerating that because
there's sort of the most training data
to train on and because it's sort of
component-based system that's lines up
with the way human beings reason about
stuff. There's a bunch of reasons why
LLMs are really good at at generating
React code and things like that. But,
what Expo is is basically like a way to
use React to write UI's that not only
work on the web, but also work on iOS
and Android and other surfaces and give
you sort of actually native apps there.
It's built on top of this technology
from React Native that it's called React
Native. It came out of
Facebook Meta. But, you can kind of
think of Expo as sort of like
the equivalent of what Next.js is in the
web world. If people don't know what
that is, that's basically like this
framework from Vercel that's become sort
of the most popular way to build a new
website using React. A lot of batteries
are included, a lot of like nice
features are just sort of like already
configured for you and set up properly.
And a lot of problems are just solved
and there's it just sort of become the
standard. And so, there's a lot of
other, you know, a lot of example code
relies on it, things like that. What we
provide with Expo is sort of a couple
different things. One is we provide this
sort of what we call the Expo SDK which
has, you know, literally a hundred
different APIs that let you have access
to all the sensors on the device, you
know, like the accelerometer, the
gyroscope, things like that. But, then
also handle, you know, basic tasks like,
you know, video and audio playback and
recording and things that you want to do
in an app like that, location services,
things like that. And generally they'll
give you access to, you know, they're
sort of multiple implementations of
these so and they're well tested and
things like that. So, they work on iOS,
they work on Android, and they work on
the web. In the same way that like a
standard library in, you know, Python or
something like that includes a lot of
the basic things you need to do or write
a program that actually does something,
you know, the Expo standard library is
basically a sort of basic batteries
included way to get started. And then we
have a bunch of tools that include Expo
Go, which is an app in the App Store
that will let you sort of get going
editing a live real app on your actual
device within seconds, which is which is
a real differentiating factor. So, a lot
of the new tools that are doing AI stuff
with development like they end up using
Expo as their way to deliver the stuff
because you can you can download Expo Go
on your phone, scan one of these QR
codes that these actual tools are
generating, and you can actually be sort
of like vibe coding or live editing your
app on the fly. And then we also provide
a suite of cloud services that is sort
of how we make money. Like we run a a
build service that runs Xcode in the
cloud and Android Studio in the cloud.
We run sort of a an update service,
which is kind of the analog of web
hosting. We also do web hosting and a
few other things. One of the beauties of
React or working in React on web or on
React Native is like live updating,
which is not something for mobile that
we had without React Native. It's like
you would build, you'd modify your
Objective-C or Swift or whatever, you'd
have to re- compile the whole app, you'd
have to deploy it to the simulator or to
the device. And it's like if you have a
small app, maybe it's 30 seconds.
Sometimes But if you have a big app,
that could be minutes. The cycle of
using, you know, well, React Native and
then Expo Go allows you to have this
like insanely tight build and change and
view cycle that was even though React
Native, I think especially in the early
days was like somewhat difficult to work
with or had it wasn't as batteries
loaded as as you've made it now with
with all the Expo stuff. If you could
get that to work, it was just crazy how
fast you could iterate. I mean, I think
that was like a huge I don't know how
much credit Expo gets for like making
React Native a thing, but I think that
made that made the developer experience
really viable and and actually like in a
lot of ways better than the native
development experience on on mobile.
Yeah, that iteration speed is a huge
reason why people have kind of moved in
this direction. Like I think a lot of
the customers that we have now, a lot of
them have actually had working like iOS,
you know, written in Swift, written in
Objective C apps, and working Android
apps that are written in Java or Kotlin,
and they just have found it's too much
work to maintain these. If you add we
wanted new features, we we can't move
fast enough on either platform, much
less both at the same time. It's really
hard to hire for these sort of
specialized positions. We're at risk all
the time before sort of one Android
person leaves, what are we going to do?
And so, a huge deal for a lot of these
companies is basically like we can move
faster than we could on either platform
by itself, but now we're able to write
one React code base. There's way more
React developers in the world than there
are basically any native platform like,
you know, Swift developers or Kotlin
developers. Yeah, it just just because
of the it's the default on the web,
right? Like creates just more Right. And
so, you can you can take your the same
pool of people you'd be hiring your
website team from and put them all on
the you know, sort of application team,
and they can work on all products all at
once. And that's a really big deal for a
lot of people. But then even on top of
that, you're still moving faster because
you're getting instead of having to
recompile every time you make a change,
you're you're usually getting the same
benefits that you would uh basically
work on a website. Like a lot of the way
to think about what Expo does is sort of
takes the things that are good about
doing web development and bring them
into the world of native mobile. Did you
guys ever get guff from Apple for like
pulling down sort of like live code? Cuz
they used they used to have like stupid
rules about this, and they I think they
relaxed them. They've really changed the
rules over time. Like they used to be
really strict and say like, you know,
you can't download any code, but then
like people would just use web views,
and then of course, the way that the web
works is it downloads much of code like
JavaScript and CSS and stuff. And then
also like big companies were just doing
it, and so it was sort of a don't ask,
don't tell policy or whatever. But then
they they kind of realized that it was
just stupid to prevent that. They
changed a lot of the rules over the last
couple of years. So, now it basically
says, you know, don't like trick people
or mislead people, but if you and you
can download code and you can run it. It
has to be sort of interpreted code, not
compiled binary code, which is fine. And
like the way that that Expo works is you
you download JavaScript or JavaScript
bytecode, and then it gets interpreted
on the device. Kind of the way that like
your web browser on your computer might
download JavaScript for a website and
and run stuff. And so,
we never had too much trouble with that
because as we were kind of starting to
get popular, Apple was in the process of
kind of pulling back a little bit from
being super duper strict about those
rules. Five years earlier, you would
have probably had a hard time, but they
were Yeah. Possibly. But, they've also
there there's maybe literally like one
or two cases where something that was
like a fintech app or something like
that, they sort of said, "Hey, we don't
want you downloading anything. We see
network requests for things that look
like they change the UI of this." It's
been a while since you've heard of
anything like that, but maybe you know,
back in the early days, we heard of one
or two things like that. But, that
that's pretty common that like Apple and
Google, but especially Apple, are are
often pretty They like to just kind of
like poke at things and sort of come up
with reasons to reject apps every once
in a while just to remind you who's in
charge, and make sure that they're like
Well, I mean, it it literally in a way
does circumvent app review, right? Like,
you can blow away an entire app. But,
The way they've changed the rules is not
to sort of say you can do whatever you
want. It's just to say it's to be more
product focused in the way that they
describe it, where like if you were to
say if you were to use this downloading
new code technology to take, you know,
an app that was for buying groceries and
turn it into some, you know, like
OnlyFans type thing, like then they
would say, "Hey, you can't just like
change this under people's feed. This
isn't what they signed up for. You're
tricking people. We're going to ban you
for that." But, it's less about the
mechanism they're using to do it, and
it's more just like the fact that you're
you're tricking users and pulling the
rug out from under them. Is it von
Neumann? Who's the one that says code
and data are the same thing? You know
what I mean? Like, it's really hard to
like differentiate, cuz you could send
JSON down that your your app
functionally interprets to like do
things, right? So, it's like it's really
difficult to say what's code and what's
not. That's the way a lot of modern apps
that like don't use Java like things
like Yelp that are older apps that are
written in, you know, Objective-C,
Swift, or whatever. They're are doing
exactly what you're describing, where
they're downloading lots of chunks of
JSON to deliver custom UI. They're sort
of like edging their way into building
sort of a half-baked dynamic interpreter
of UIs. Basically React rendering a
scene graph or I don't know what the
what it's called in in React land, but
there's a kind of moderately famous like
old CS quote that's sort of like any
sufficiently complicated, you know,
system in C++ contains a
half-working, you know, inefficient
version of Lisp or something like that.
And it's kind of the same thing that
you're describing. Well, one of the
things that I did want to kind of talk
through is that the combination of React
Native and Expo, especially, have kind
of become a new default. And you you
quoted in our our state of subscription
apps report that the Pragmatic Engineer
reported that almost all new VC-funded
startups are using React Native versus
building native. And huge apps, Spotify,
Discord, NFL, you know, tons of the
biggest apps that people interact with
on a daily basis are built in React
Native. The movie kind of already
touched on it, speed of execution, being
able to, you know, change things
remotely. But do you think building apps
with native code is less important in
2025? And why?
There's a couple things going on.
One is just there's a general
improvement in the technology. You see
this happen all over the place where
like writing stuff in client-side
JavaScript didn't make sense in like
2004 cuz it just all the features you
needed weren't there and the performance
of JS VMs wasn't there, etc. etc. And
then things just get faster and better.
That's one part of what's happening
here, where there's a lot of stuff
that's happened in the space. Like some
of it's like pretty low-level. Meta is
responsible for like two of these
things, and it's great to have sort of a
deep-pocketed
company behind a lot of this that like
relies on it for a lot of poor things.
And so two really important things that
have happened in the ecosystem are this
new JS VM called Hermes, which is
actually like I don't know if you want
me to go too much in the weeds here, but
basically like there's um you know, the
the most famous JS VM these days is is
like the one that Google made for Chrome
called V8. And that's a really great JS
VM or it you know, really moved the web
forward. It moved JS forward. It's a a
jitting VM and so it like does
just-in-time compilation of your code
and so like you know, as your code is
running for the first couple times,
it'll sort of track the hot paths and
sort of compile those on the fly and
they'll run faster. But in UIs you
actually don't really
want that a lot of times because you're
not doing lots of like complicated
computations of or mathy type things.
You're just like trying to like run
through stuff once and put stuff on the
screen. And so you actually want to op
and like a lot of times when you think
about what you want in UIs, you want it
to be like that first interaction comes
as quickly as possible rather than like
you start running faster and faster as
your code runs over time.
It's really good at passing some certain
benchmark, but not actually what matters
for scene graph rendering.
Because of Apple's restrictions on sort
of native code execution, you can't
really run a jit on an interpreter. That
was going to be what I asked like what
the status on that was cuz I didn't
think you you famously like Apple
wouldn't allow this for uh sensibly but
probably legitimately security reasons.
Yeah, I think that's it's like not crazy
that they they restrict stuff in this
way. So Hermes is designed to not jit
for performance reasons in a interesting
way. And it's really designed for this
use case in particular and a few others.
And it also you know, it uses a bytecode
format. So like instead of just sending
down you know, strings of text that are
human-readable, it sort of pre-compiles
into sort of more intermediate format
and gets sent that down. That saves some
time. That just boosted performance
especially on low-end Android, but
across the board Hermes is a big step.
And there's also something called the
new architecture of Native that like,
you know, it's been talked about for
years and finally in the last year it's
now rolled out and sort of the default
of new Expo apps and new React Native
apps is to use this new architecture. It
allows a lot more control over low-level
stuff that you actually want to really
optimize the performance of things like
lists are really important to UIs on
mobile. Like almost every app that you
use involves like
scrolling through lots of lists. You
know, think about Instagram, think about
any messenger you use.
UI list view, I think famously was like
the singular most important component of
Cocoa originally cuz it was just super
optimized and so fast and what made the
original iPhone feel so good. And so one
thing that this new architecture enables
is just like you can write much faster
lists because you can sort of
synchronously measure elements and react
to those changes without having to go
through lots of re-rendering steps. I'm
like glossing over a lot of stuff there,
but basically this new architecture is a
a big step forward in terms of
performance possibilities and a few
other things. The other thing that's
happened
is you sort of
the way you pose this question was like,
is it less important to write native
code on mobile? But actually one thing
that we spent a while doing at Expo was
making it a lot easier to write native
code as part of a React Native app. And
so like part of the sort of dream of
React Native was always that you're
actually interweaving stuff that's like
native code with stuff that's like
orchestrated by JavaScript.
writing React for web, how you can
interleave like HTML basically, right?
Like style within your JavaScript, you
know? Like you can kind of like
seamlessly like write components out and
then switch back and forth. It's kind of
like that. And um and React Native like
when you generate like a UI a view or uh
you know, a list view or a scroll view,
one of the things that's really
appealing about React Native is it's
actually generating like the operating
system components. So like
a view in React Native on iOS will
generate a UI view from UI Kit and on
Android you and so like the actual
elements that you're interacting with
should feel exactly right to the
operating system you're on. But then if
you do need to write some sort of
specialized native code to do some sort
of fluid simulation or some really
custom video player or something like
that or some view that pops up a native
share dialogue or native payments
dialogue or something like that, you can
easily drop down into native code and
write that stuff. A big thing that we
worked on at Expo is we This gets a
little bit This gets a little bit but
it's actually pretty important. We
developed this thing that we call config
plugins and CNG.
And the sort of way that you would do
native code in React Native projects
before that was kind of the same way
that you might have like dealt with like
PHP extensions back in the day or like
weaving together C++ code with like a
scripting language where you're doing a
lot of like compiling stuff yourself,
figuring out which things you need to
download and which dependencies you need
to download and like how to put them all
in the in the right place.
And then like if you were making in my
my my shoes trying to make a React
Native SDK that somebody else could then
go use that was based on native code, it
was rough.
Really really rough to do. And so like
all a lot of these projects would have,
you know, you go to the GitHub for it
and the read me is sort of like a four
or five page long thing with like here's
all the steps you need to do on Android,
here's all the steps you need to do on
iOS. And then if you're bringing in the
RevenueCat module and a special video
player module and a camera module, a lot
of times those things would actually the
instructions whatever you're editing
various config files and whatnot and
they might step on each other's toes.
Like hey, in this app delegate add this
add these lines and then you're like,
well, those lines that doesn't look the
way I it says it's going to look because
I added this other module or whatever.
And so what config plugins are are
basically sort of in your module you can
add sort of a set of instructions or
scripts that basically like tell the
native code how to install itself in a
generalized way. And then what CNG is is
continuous native generation. And so in
a typical like old school React Native
project, you'd have like your JavaScript
source directory that that has like your
React code. And then you have like an
Android directory and iOS directory
where sort of like the special native
code for Android and iOS would live. And
in a sort of Expo project using CNG,
you don't have the Android and the iOS
directory typically living in your
project cuz they get generated every
time that you make a change to the set
of config plugins you use. They're
almost like at machine code now, right?
Like they're kind of like halfway
between. When you NPM install some
package, it like figures out what needs
to get downloaded and kind of moves
those files into the right directory and
kind of makes it so that you can just
sort of require that in your or import
it in your project and it just kind of
work. And you can kind of think of it as
the same thing where you can just kind
of one command to install a new, you
know, React Native purchases or some
other package and then all of the setup
just gets taken care of. And if you
upgrade to a new version of React Native
or new native stuff, all that stuff it
just sort of happens seamlessly. It's
gotten way, way easier to actually use
native code. And so even for people that
like
think native code is really important,
it's gotten much more sensible to use
React Native than it was in the past
because it's a lot easier to access the
native layers of stuff. The way a lot of
people probably look at it is like if
you think about what's going on in the
world of AI, obviously performance is
super important in you know, doing all
this machine learning type stuff, etc.
etc. But a lot of the code that people
who, you know, work on optimizing these
models at OpenAI or or playing around
with these things, they're running a lot
of Python because
some things need to be really, really
fast, but a lot of stuff doesn't need to
be really, really fast. You're just sort
of saying, "Go do this task that has to
be really, really fast." And you're sort
of orchestrating things. And so you see
this happening in a lot of systems. And
so that's that's one big factor. Another
factor is like, you know, a couple of
years ago engineers were sort of
considered assets to tech companies. And
so people were trying to hire, you know,
"If I can hire 100 people, I'm worth
$100 million or something." is is a blog
post I read. And like people are not
thinking that way anymore. A lot of the
companies that we talked to that are
using Expo, they they even had like
working iOS apps that were well
reviewed, perfectly fine, and you know,
good Android apps that were also in sync
with that and perfectly functional, but
they were just finding it was really
hard to move forward quickly, really
hard to keep those things in sync,
really hard to hire for these positions,
and also they just like they were really
at risk if they were to lose their one
Android developer or their one iOS
developer, and they just be stuck and
unable to like keep their their product
going. And so, Creates some really
awkward choices, too, when you're like,
"Oh, we want to experiment with
something." But then you kind of are
forced to not do parity. You have to do
it on one platform and then backport it,
and then that backport never happens
because like you're busy and yeah. And
now your all of your documentation to
your users and your customer service
team is getting confused and has to ask
more questions. There's just all kinds
of things that are, you know, bad news
about going in that path. In general,
like
there used to be this idea that like,
you know, your Android users have
fundamentally different expectations
than iOS users, and the web is its own
beast. And so, like if you go
rewind time back to say like, you know,
2011, and like Dropbox and Slack were
two pretty good examples of this where
they had totally separate design teams
working on their Android and iOS
products. And so, if you like switch
from an Android phone to an iOS phone or
vice versa, and you're using Dropbox or
using Slack, you'd just be like,
"I don't know where anything is. What
the heck is this?" Because it's just
like a totally different product. And
now things have really gone pretty far
in the other direction where Conversion
evolution, right? Like it turns out that
there's only a so many ways to like make
a decent mobile app. want basically the
same product on iOS and Android and web.
And if so, like when I use the United
Airlines app on my phone, whether it's
on iPhone or my Android phone or the
mobile website or the website, it's
basically the same product, same design
language. Things are all in basically
the same places. I don't think United
Airlines actually uses React Native.
They might, but I'm I don't believe it.
I just think like
the general thinking around product is
moving in that direction. But then once
your thinking around product moves in
that direction, you're like, "Why
doesn't our implementation match the way
that we're actually building product?
Oh, I see what you're saying. So the
actual the actual conformity comes
first. Like that we should just have
things be identical. And then from then
it follows like why do we have these
like separate tool chains, right? Yeah.
And then another thing that's kind of
come online is we did a lot of work to
make Expo work on web as well as iOS and
Android. So a lot of the people now that
use Expo actually going to have one team
across iOS and Android and web. And so
it's not just a mobile only thing. So
one of the most prominent exciting Expo
apps is Blue Sky, which is like feels
really good. And like I find it
basically as good as an app. Missing a
few, you know, advanced video features
and stuff, but otherwise like pretty
comparable to Twitter and all those
feels great. But they had their sort of
thing they'll say is like one man, three
platforms, four months was how they
built their the first version of it
because they weren't even planning to
build an app. It's a complicated sort of
origin story, but you know, when Jack
Dorsey was sort of thinking about how
social media needed to evolve and how it
could be federated, he sort of allocated
some funding for a federated kind of
protocol. But they were really just
imagining they would make a protocol for
how to federate something like Twitter.
And that Twitter would be the first
client of this protocol. And then, you
know, you almost got Twitter just sort
of like, why do I need this, you know,
I'm trying to cut everything and make
this a lean and mean machine. I don't
need to deal with this. But they had
incorporated as a separate company and
sort of the funding was sort of already
earmarked for it. So they were able to
keep going, but they, you know, they
were looking around and they're like, we
have like a 10-person team and we have
no developers who are iOS developers or
Android developers. And we're on a kind
of tight time on here. We need And we
realized like our only way forward is to
actually make an app to be the flagship
version of our, you know, federated
protocol. And so they just had Paul on
their team didn't even have React
experience. And he just learned on the
fly and he was he just a really sharp
guy with pretty good taste and was able
to make something pretty good out of the
gate. And they've still only have about
three people working on the app and it
works across all the different
platforms. And so it's one they have one
code base for their web. That's like
extreme React UI, right? Like to be able
to scale. That's crazy. One thing I
we talking about the Facebook
investments. Who is doing most of the
work on that last translation layer now
from like your scene graph to rendering
in native UIs and stuff? Is Facebook
still developing a lot of that? Is it
handled by the community? Cuz I imagine
a lot of what makes React Native plus
Expo work really well is kind of that
like last mile translating it to the
platform. Well, a lot of that kind of
doesn't need as much like change as you
might think. One reason it works pretty
well in a lot of ways is that there's
it's not a super heavy layer.
I'm glossing over a bit here,
but like if you make a view in React
Native like, you know, you know, you use
angle brackets and you write view,
you're writing some React code.
When that targets web, that's just going
to turn into a div. There isn't some
sort of like
crazy like giant transformation. You can
kind of reason about how it's going to
end up running. And when you have that
view and it goes on iOS, it's going to
end up with just like a UI view from UI
Kit. And like there's a little bit of
wrapping and other kinds of things that
go on there. And like basically like a
lot of what we think of as apps is just
sort of like rectangles and sort of
coloring and styling and text and then
some images and things like that. And so
there is work to do. Like we released
something not that long ago called Expo
image, which you know, a lot of people
are using things like SD web image and
fast image and certain like things that
will handle caching and different
formats and things like that. And uh we
kind of like some of those weren't that
well maintained and so we just sort of
decided this is something we should
build ourselves and pull it to the SDK
and sort of standardize and whatnot. So
we do a lot of that. There's also a lot
of the innovation that's happening right
now that's pretty good for the space is,
you know, expectations of what we expect
from products have gone up a lot. This
is true on the web, kind of double true
on mobile, but if you think back to
like, you know, a web 15 years ago or
something, what you'd expect from a
website is you wouldn't expect any kind
of like 3D graphics or, you know,
interesting transitions or whatever, but
now you even go to like some random
product page for something and a lot of
times you'll scroll down and some sort
of crazy 3D animation will happen as you
scroll or something like that. And a lot
of this is like WebGL and just like
things for doing that on the web have
advanced a lot. And so, if you want to
add a lot of really nice touches to uh
sort of
React Native app or something like that,
there's some really good libraries out
there like React Native Skia, which adds
the sort of Skia 2D graphics engine. And
then there's, you know, at this
conference I'm at today, there was just
some announcements around React Native
WebGPU and having access to that. And
then there's something called
Reanimated, made by a a firm in Poland
called Software Mansion. They also have
something called React Native Gesture
Handler that like like these powerful
libraries that let you get all these
gestures and animations
to be really right, but also be like
things that you can write in just
JavaScript instead of having to go write
a bunch of custom native code to make
something like look and feel really
cool. Now getting back into the
multi-platform problem, right? Where you
have to like do some like native stuff.
It sounds like stuff's really
accelerating. I I think there was a I
don't know when this was, but there was
a moment, maybe it was 5 years ago, when
like Facebook kind of dropped React
Native and there was like a lot of flood
about maybe React Native's over, but it
seems like that that's the opposite.
Now, is that was that always just a fake
news or what was the story? There were a
couple things that were challenging. The
most damaging thing that probably ever
happened in the history of React Native
is the Airbnb was kind of an early user
of it and they, you know, they had a
couple of guys there that were really
good developers and and you know,
contributed a lot and they they'd go
around at a lot of conferences and talk
about their work. For a bunch of like
complicated reasons, the engineering
team at Airbnb just decided like it
doesn't make sense to kind of maintain
our sort of native stuff and our React
Native stuff and we decided that like
the native people kind of win.
And so like we're going to just stop
doing this. And they were never a fully
React Native app though. They had like
React Native components. No, they were
using it for like you know 20% of the
app or something like that but they were
just they were pretty vocal about it.
Which is less you get less benefit then
right? Like if you have like a native
and It's somewhat complicated to kind of
have a really mixed brown field type
approach like
it's more complicated than having a
website that was using jQuery and then
is using React for one of the screens.
Because in a website you're using
JavaScript everywhere and so if you have
some data that's pulled down by a jQuery
Ajax call and then you want to use it
inside of a React component or reuse
some of the same state you can just pass
those variables back and forth or refer
to them. And this is just like one
example just to illustrate the point.
But like let's say that you had you know
a screen on Airbnb's app that's written
in Swift and then you know another part
of that screen is written in React
Native. And then it's relying on you
know some profile for a house listing
and that house listing has some data and
has like a you know URL of a photo or
something like that. And you pull down
that data in Swift and it's now in like
Swift variables and then all of a sudden
you're like
React Native wants to access to the same
photo to make sure it's the right thing
or it wants to you know do highlight
something and like that data isn't
available in JavaScript you have to kind
of create some sort of way to you know
marshal things across some bridge and
what not. Bridge and then now you at a
minimum you're probably duplicating your
memory consumption right? And it just
gets like there's different ways you can
handle it but it's it's sort of like you
now have it's almost like you have this
like
three things to worry about like your
native your native world your JavaScript
world and then the way to move between
them. And so now like a lot of things
that are I think that's something I
really want to work on is making that
sort of incremental transition easier.
But in the world where we are now
definitely the things that are having
the most success that we see are things
that kind of start from the beginning as
React Native apps. They might use a lot
of native code, but it's usually in this
way where it's like, "Oh, we're going to
do some really specific stuff, like have
a custom video player, but it's going to
be a React Native module and that can
just sort of plug in and we can drop
down to native code wherever we need to,
but the whole system is kind of being
orchestrated and controlled by by React
Native." Another thing that
you know, when I was talking about the
transition to this being pretty standard
is a thing that we spent a lot of time
on was Evan Bacon on our team, who was
amazing, spearheaded this work on
something called Expo Router, which is
pretty common in the world of React or
websites to have a sort of router thing
that will handle, you know, just a
mapping out like the architecture of
like all the tabs in your screen or like
what URLs map to and what what not. It's
a much more complicated pro- problem on
this sort of multi-platform mobile type
thing because if you think about like
this is probably something that like
anybody can kind of understand if they
stop and think about it for a minute,
but most of us don't. We're like, on the
web, the structure of websites is that
you have this URL bar and there's kind
of a back button and like
it means that like there's kind of one
stack of like navigation in a lot of
cases, where if you think about, you
know, everybody probably is familiar
with Instagram who's who's listening to
this podcast. And and that's a pretty
common paradigm where there's like four
or five tabs at the bottom of your
screen and each of those is kind of its
own stack. And so if you, you know, go
to your profile tab and then you tap on
followers and then you tap on somebody
else's profile. That's like all
happening underneath the profile tab,
but then if you go to the search tab,
you can go look at somebody else's
profile, but then if you go back to your
own profile tab, it's still whatever
you've navigated to and there's kind of
like multiple hierarchies of stuff going
on. And so when you're making an app
that like exists as a mobile app, you
often want that paradigm that's more
like the Instagram app, but then when
you're on the web, you want it to feel
like a website and be natural in that
way. And then there's also this deep
linking is this gnarly problem that is
actually pretty hard to get right. Where
like if you think about like anything
you have an app installed for, they
might send you an email that has like a
you know, hey like check out this
listing you know, for this product for
sale on our app or whatever. And then
you tap in the link and it like opens
the app and it just is like gets
confused and takes you to the home
screen and you're like, I was trying to
get to the specific product or the
specific video. It's about 50/50 I feel
like when I deep link into an app if I'm
going to get where I'm trying to go.
Yeah, and so Expo router handles that
and just like works basically as well as
anything can work across iOS and Android
and web and just that problem just
becomes
a thing that's solved for you rather
than a thing that you spend hours and
hours and hours trying to get right and
and stressing about and whatever. And so
that's a a very nice thing that's just
made it a lot easier for people to
adopt. In researching for this podcast
and then now in listening to you for the
last you know, 30 minutes or so, I've
updated my priors a lot and you know, I
was one of those like snooty iOS
developers who was like, oh and you
know, that was like so focused on oh
it's it's got to be native like React
Native just a you know, lame web wrapper
and like users are going to notice the
performance is not going to be there.
It's going to be more complicated and
like all of that is which may have been
true in 2019 or 18, but maybe not today.
On the web, you can always view source
and so you can kind of always figure out
whatever any website is built with. But
one thing that's I've always found funny
is like when somebody does an awesome
job building a React Native app,
you don't notice and you just assume
that it's like you know, truly native or
whatever like that.
pretty trash Swift UI and UI Kit apps
too, right? I've seen them. Right. And
so so there are some bad React Native
and bad Expo apps out there that are
just like you know,
unnecessarily causing all kinds of
re-renders or loops or whatever. And you
know, and you but you can also do that
as you're saying with Swift UI or
whatever. Like a lot of times they'll be
like a bad Swift UI app and people will
just be "Oh, stupid React Native. I can
tell that this is
And like, because there's no there's no
easy way to kind of do a view source
search. Have you ever done any like uh
blind taste tests? That'd be very funny
to like
James and Brent on our team, I think
used to be pretty good about being able
to sort of Oh, I'm going to drag this
screens, and like I'll I'll notice some,
you know, artifact in this thing, and I
can tell that that's using this library.
And stuff like that. It's getting
harder, but there's still some ways that
you can tell certain things for sure.
But, we've also tried scanning the App
Store and downloading a lot of the top
apps and just sort of like we did a
research project to basically just
figure out what cuz we're an open source
product. So, we don't actually know
everybody who's using Expo. If you're
just using the open source framework, we
don't know. So, we had to download it
just like the top 100 apps in every
category just to get a sense of of what
was going on there. So, talking about
updating my priors, the biggest thing
that forced me to update my priors is
actually our state of subscription app
report. And that's what I wanted to talk
about next is that in our report, we
showed that React Native apps actually
monetize better than native apps.
There's probably a little bit of 100%
positive. It's all the framework data.
There's probably a little bit of bias in
that, and then we talked about this
before, that, you know, we have a ton of
indie developers on on RevenueCat who
are iOS only, and that, you know, to our
point earlier, a lot of the VC-funded
apps are cross-platform from the
beginning and kind of building a
business, not a hobby, tend towards
React Native. So, there there's some
bias in the data. And and you kind of
alluded to this to this earlier, that
what matters is your product. And if
you're able to iterate more quickly,
build a better product, it doesn't
matter what technology you're using. And
and in fact, maybe it does in that React
Native lets you move quicker, and that
you don't have multiple teams, you don't
have things getting out of sync and
stuff like that. But, I know you saw
that data cuz, you know, we we had you
do a little blurb in our report, but did
that surprise you to see our data that
React Native apps are monetizing better
than native apps? It's is surprising to
me just because like
I would have expected that a lot of the,
you know, native apps would be iPhone
only and like iPhone tends to monetize
better than Android in my limited I
mean, you guys would know better than I
would, but But it's almost always like
it's iOS and Android, right? So, the
Android's almost probably always like
incremental. I could see something here
where it's just like a lot of people
using React like you're going to have
more React Native apps that are newer
because React Native is just I certainly
Expo has gotten, you know, way more
popular recently like our
our NPM weekly downloads have tripled in
the past year, for example. So, like a
lot of stuff that's built that way is
going to be newer and it's going to have
people people making active choices like
researching the best way to do stuff and
working on things and trying to use the
best technologies and best practices,
whereas some of the older stuff might
just be kind of like this project's been
around a while, it's kind of been, you
know, cruise control mode. Like I'm not
saying maintenance mode, but just kind
of like we're just trying to keep this
running or whatever. That would be part
of the the guess I would make. But also
would just sort of like bring up the
point again that like whenever you need
to in React Native, it's now quite easy
to drop down and write, you know, a
whole screen in SwiftUI and Kotlin, you
know, Kotlin or whatever you want for
the specific platforms. And so like if
you're a good React Native developer,
you're probably doing that at various
points whenever you need to. But like,
you know, under setting screen,
you basically don't ever need to do that
in most cases. Like you those are the
kind of things that in a lot of even
a lot of parts of the actual iOS
settings app, like if you go into like
your manage your subscriptions of your
iOS app a lot of stuff has actually been
using like web views even though we
think of it as sort of like native to
the Apple platform. Oh, yeah, yeah, like
the subscription one. It drives me nuts.
It's like it is markedly slower. It
would be better if React Native Yeah,
they should use
They would never. They would never dare
put JavaScript between them and UI Kit.
But I think a big part of it is like the
ceiling gone up on just being it's a lot
easier to access the the best
capabilities of the device than it used
to be. My two cents is it's probably all
I mean, not no no knocks to React Native
uh and Expo, but like, you know, it's
very much a selection bias thing. Like,
if you are more focused on business
success and business outcomes, which
maybe is like that's a great like it's a
great argument for the the platform,
right? Like and I think
and like David was saying is I think if
you're mobile if you're a native mobile
developer, like I think it is time to at
least like give it a try and re-evaluate
your priors cuz I've built apps in React
Native. It's been frustrating in
different ways, but this was 5-6 years
ago, right? And like things have
changed. It's gotten way way better, way
easier to make stuff. Yeah, thanks to
you guys and and also just like baseline
technology changes. Phones are faster as
well. And so, I remember in the late
teens being skeptical of people that
were making this choice cuz I was
tried and true mobile Objective-C and
Java developer. And I remember being
skeptical, but now looking back, these
companies have had various success and
not success, but none of it was like
hurt by the fact that they were you
know, in fact like I think are you for
all the reasons we talked about today, I
think it was it was these these were
good choices. Depends on the business
you're in, too. And then now today, you
know, speaking of making things easier,
the next kind of topics I wanted to
discuss was AI-assisted development. I
did want to kind of cage these two
different things cuz I think they get
blended a little bit. So, we'll talk
first about what I'm calling AI-assisted
app development where you're a
programmer, you know what you're doing,
and AI is accelerating things whether
using React Native or not. And then you
have the the kind of vibe coding of like
I'm going to, you know, jump into Bolt
or Replit and throw a few prompts in
there and I don't really know how to
code, but it's going to build an app.
Let's talk first about what you're
seeing in that AI-assisted app
development loop of like really
top-notch programmers using AI and React
to just move quicker using things like
Cursor and Windsurf and GitHub Copilot
and Cloud Code and all these kind of
tools to move faster. What are you
seeing there? And also maybe like what
Expo's like kind of a unique position
right now in this world, which I think
is interesting. For that kind of stuff,
one thing that's really a big deal is
like, how well trained are the models
and the stuff that you're having it
write. And one thing that's just good
about React is just a ton of open-source
example code out there. And people tend
It's It's much more common to make like
a React project open source than it is
to make like a Swift project. These LLMs
are actually pretty good at like
figuring most things out to some degree,
but just the more training data they
have, the better they're going to be and
whatnot. So like there's 1.2 million
plus Expo products that are open source
on GitHub right now. And some of those
are old and out of date, and that can
cause its own That's its own sort of
niche problem or whatever. But a big
part of it is just like, there's that.
But then
another thing that happens is that like,
when you have this sort of AI-assisted
coding in your developer,
actually I was teaching a workshop the
other day at a a college,
and a few years ago when I would do
that, a lot of the time I would spend in
this when I was teaching a workshop
making a basic app would just be me
typing out line, you know, basic stuff
of state management or, you know, going
to our docs to look up the right, you
know, thing to you know, the right
incantation to import the camera module
or things like that. And then I just was
like, in 5 minutes I had sort of like
built a whole to-do list app and added a
couple features to it. And I was just
sort of like, "Okay, class. I'm not
going to have you watch me use Claude
for the rest of this session. Just like
come up to me if you have problems and
I'll just talk to you guys." The time it
takes to do basic stuff just goes way,
way down. And so when that's happening,
we start to get super sensitive to the
things that start to take a lot of time
and slow you down. And so, you know, I'm
sure you guys have seen that famous XKCD
comic where there's the the guy's like
cardboard sword fighting in the in the
spinny chairs where they're waiting for
things to compile. And so like when it's
taking you like a split second to write
code and then all of a sudden you're
spending a minute and 45 seconds as your
app the
sort of nasty thing about sort of
compiled apps and stuff like that. They
start off kind of like when you have
a white screen with like one thing of
black text on a that just says like
hello, it's like compilation is pretty
quick. But then you you when you get to
start six seven screens that are pretty
it's like
Or get submodules, SPM, CocoaPods
somehow both in the same project, yeah.
Yeah, all of a sudden that's now 45
seconds, a minute 45 and it just sort of
big companies that have these huge
sprawling apps like Uber if it like a
huge chunk of the engineering and and
stuff is like
it takes 45 minutes plus to compile our
app. And so people are going off and
making new projects where they're
building new UIs and then trying to sort
of copy-paste them over as a crazy
stuff. So anyway, tangent, but you can
imagine that like waiting for stuff to
compile when you're not really spending
any time writing code just becomes super
super painful. And so like the idea that
you can just like make a quick change,
you save it and that UI is now updated
on your phone or or on your simulator or
whatever right away, that just feels so
much better. And that bottleneck is
really exposed as it's you really
ratchet down the amount of time that
you're spending writing code. Sort of
similar principle is happening with live
coding as well where like models like
Claude and Gemini or whatever are like
decent at writing Swift code or
whatever. That's actually kind of
exciting for React Native because well,
I was just talking to someone the other
day who's a really good React Native
developer. This guy Fernando who's the
head of mobile at Vercel. He was saying
a lot of what he's been doing lately is
doing more stuff in Swift on iOS because
he doesn't have to become a Swift
expert. He can kind of like when he
wants to go do something, he can just
kind of like have AI
point him in the right direction, clean
up stuff and make it kind of make it
work. And so he's able to write more
stuff in native code. So like LLMs are
actually decent at writing that stuff.
But like, imagine you're a vibe coder
and you're just like, "Hey, I want to
try I heard that I can make stuff as a
you know, just vibe coding now." And you
decide you want to do that by writing
some Swift code. And then it's like,
"Okay, well, first of all, you need to
have a Mac. Only what, 12% of computers
globally are Macs?" Okay, so now a lot
of people are just like stuck and they
can't do anything. But let's say you do
have a Mac and let's say it's a fast Mac
or whatever. And it's kind of like,
"Okay, now here's your next instruction
is download Xcode." And that often takes
like 45 minutes. And then setting it up
is like another, you know, 45 minutes of
$99 sign up to the Apple developer
program. You need a DUNS number. No, you
don't have to do that, but like
need a DUNS number until you want to go
to the App Store, but like, you know, it
literally can take you 3 days before you
get at your developer account approved.
You don't need a developer account
anymore to just put something on your
own device. But like
And not even the simulator actually on
your end device. You can do it without.
Yeah, you can If you plug your phone
into your computer, it's pretty handy.
It's capped in a lot of ways, but they
they're a little bit more lax. Like the
mindset just seems to be like, it's a
privilege that you would be able to
write any software on these devices that
are are sort of pristine playgrounds. I
mean, I won't do back in my day, but
it's a heck of a lot easier now.
It's gotten easier, but it's still not
like actively easy. It's like you're
there's just sort of a whole bunch of
hurdles.
Opening an HTML file in Chrome, you
know, and you boom, you're running.
Expo is just like a bunch of different
tools and I like it'll take me a long
time to explain all of them, but like
one of them is this Expo Go app that you
can download from the App Store. And
that has
basically just like most of the modules
in the Expo SDK kind of baked into it
already. And so if you just want to use
the camera view or location or the
gyroscope or any of the sort of basic
things, those are already just like
baked in natively. And so
that covers a lot of ground for a lot of
people. And so if you can write stuff
that has you know, you can use any font
you want. You can do any kind of styling
you want. You can do any kind of things
with even has React Native Skia built
into it. And so you can do like pretty
complex stuff with just this. And so a
lot of the Vibe Coder stuff basically
just is like, here here's your
instructions. Download the Expo Go app
from the App Store. We're popping a QR
code up on your screen. Scan the QR
code. Bam.
In less than 30-40 seconds, you now have
your app on your phone. As you make
changes to it, you're and you're writing
stuff, that's just happening. So, like I
was just up in Seattle this place called
like the AI It's sort of a complicated
thing that's like a incubator plus event
space plus co-working space. The person
who runs the the sort of physical space
there is telling me that they needed
some sort of check-in You know, a lot of
offices have like the sort of check-in
step where you go up to the desk and
they have an iPad and you sort of fill
out your name and who you're going to
visit and whatnot. And she was saying
that like because they're the sort of
hybrid of a uh you know, a couple
different things all at once, none of
the sort of off-the-shelf solutions were
exactly what they needed. But, they also
didn't need something like super crazy
complicated cuz it's just like they
don't have a hundred locations. They
just have this like one space. She's not
a uh you know, traditionally trained
developer or anything. But, she was able
to just fire up Bolt with Expo and like
build an app just vibe coding that like,
you know, has their whole list of
experts connected to that database and
then has a whole sign-up form and you
can sign your name and then it submits
it and it stores it in a you know, a
Postgres database in the cloud using
Supabase and they can you know, access
it and
she was able to do that in a couple of
hours just sort of like, you know,
repeatedly prompting, not editing any of
the code.
To which would like comparative even an
expert developer that would take a week,
you know, to make it work, right? Yeah,
probably. That's actually like live now.
Like it using some of the Expo tools to
help get stuff into sort of TestFlight.
Like a lot of what we actually do is
just solving this distribution problem
of like, hey, I want to I want to take
this app and get it So, it's great that
you get you can get up and running in
the Go app. I mean, I I know you guys
still do a lot. I think I think the
thing that's made Expo one of the things
that's made Expo so relevant all of a
sudden for for all these people is like
that last mile on mobile is so painful,
right? So, it's great you can vibe code
something up in a in it's in you know,
it's basically running in a browser, but
then like okay, you want to get on the
App Store. Right. And so, a lot of what
we've been working on the last year or
two is stuff to like like we just
released a module not that long ago
called like NPM TestFlight where you can
basically in an Xcode project run NPM
TestFlight and it'll just like walk you
through all the steps and put it in
TestFlight and you don't have to like
you're not thinking about provisioning
profiles, you're not thinking about
distribution certificates. All these
things that are just like I feel like
I've talked to so many people who are in
the mobile world and if if you like sort
of get them aside aside and you're like
explain to me what a provisioning
profile is, they're kind of like Oh,
Charlie, I'm probably one of the few
people that could actually do a really
good job, but Right. I'm sure but like
knowledge I would love to free up in my
head. Trust me. Right. And there's a lot
of people who are like I don't I just
kind of like keep refreshing things or
Googling things until it finally works.
added at some point in X in Xcode, they
added like a fix my provisioning profile
button which
worst. Like never click that button.
Yeah, which is like actually like roll
the dice and maybe nuke my own developer
profile.
There's still some sort of rough edges
around there because Apple just like
wants to stay in control of stuff and
they it's hard to make something that's
perfect. But we we put a lot of work
into making it so that like getting up
and running on the web because we added
web hosting and stuff like that or
getting up and running through
TestFlight or the App Store or whatever.
All these things have been a lot easier.
Like a a really good flow that a lot of
people like is we actually run Xcode and
Android Studio in the cloud for people.
That's sort of one of the main ways that
we make money as a company. And if you
don't have a Mac or you don't have a
fast computer, that's just like pretty
nice. But it also means that like you're
not grinding your computer to a halt.
Every time you do a check-in, it's easy
to have a cloud build to kick off. But
then we can also take that artifact and
just submit it for you or put it in
TestFlight or just do whatever wherever
that artifact needs to go, we can sort
of solve those problems for we can run a
bunch you can have you know, a bunch of
scripted tests run against it and then
you know, a report generated whatnot.
So, solving a lot of these problems is
like a big part of what we've just kind
of realized that people need to go from,
you know, idea to living thing that's
running, you know, in production the way
they want it to be. You mentioned
there's like Bolt and and Replit and
Lovable and A0, there's a bunch of
these, and most of them are going
through you. Do you think that that's
the way things are going to shake out?
Like if I cuz I'm waiting for us as an
infrastructure company, too, like
depends on your belief in AGI, like
whether or not you can be like build
Expo, you know, as like a as like a
command line thing. Do you think these
companies continue to like run through a
like centralized service provider or do
you think they're going to need to own
this? I guess it it's There comes out a
question of like where the value accrues
and stuff or or or maybe you can even
say are are you guys thinking about just
owning the the vibe coding layer? Like
where do you think it goes? Developers
want to do all kinds of things in all
different ways. And so like if we
were to just every time where we sort of
said, "Well, we think that probably most
people want to do this, so let's just
sort of assume that and build everything
around that." We end up with a whole
bunch of people like, "Actually, I want
to do something really weird and or I
need to because I think there's just
going to be actually a pretty wide
variety of of different things. The
other side of that coin is that like I
think one thing that I've noticed about
AI-generated code and whatnot is that it
works better in general the more you
kind of keep it on the rails.
And so a big step forward for for Bolt
and Lovable
was when they both took Supabase and
made that sort of the the sort of
this is the way that we do a back end
for you. And and sure part of that was
just sort of like connecting Supabase
and making it easy to set up an account,
but I think another part of it is
probably they were tweaking the sort of
system prompts of of what they did is
just saying, "When you do a back end,
here's the rules. Like use Supabase,
keep the Make sure that you don't leak
the private key into the clients, you
know, just like do these things in this
way." And and so I think that makes it
in a lot of ways like make more sense to
rely on like a standard very popular
provider because there's going to be
good training data on that. It's going
to Everyone's going to kind of know how
to work with it and whatnot. I think
that we're still in, you know, early
days and whatnot, but I do think that
like I think that we'll see a lot of
winners win harder because like people
will just like get started and not want
to fight the AI that has just sort of
been sort of trained to like, "Oh, use
this solution." Or you like I mean, you
could probably get it an AI to generate
a Svelte website or or something like
that these days. Like if you just said,
"Please use Svelte." But like if you
just sort of say like, "Go make me a
website." Like almost every model is
going to default to to doing React and
sort of lean that direction.
probably tell you to go to Expo, too,
right? Like you're like, "How do I get
this on my phone?" It's probably nine
times out of 10 going to tell you like
this we see a lot for RevenueCat. It's
like, "How do I purchase this?" They're
like, "Do all this or go to
revenuecat.com, right?" Like that's an
option. I think a lot of things that are
just like easier and cut out the other
annoying stuff like you're saying like,
"Or go to revenuecat.com." And like a
lot of the problems that you were going
to face are just sort of go away or
handled by this. People I think are just
going to have a lot less patience for
these sort of other steps or this sort
of wandering in the forest trying to get
some complicated thing to work. I sort
of have like a an argument a gradient
descent argument where like if the
energy it requires to like send somebody
to RevenueCat or Expo or whatever is
always less than like the energy it
would take to generate the tokens like
the model should just optimize towards
like that outcome, right? Which which is
a fancy way of things basically saying
what you're saying, which is like if
it's already a relative minimum like
it's going to like continue to reinforce
that, right? Like using Superbase and
and whatever versus like when it's
exploring new space, which is what the
vibe codes are actually building. That's
where the model should be spending most
of its energy. I also think there's
stuff where like a lot of the people
that are making these, you know,
web-based fronts for AIs and whatnot
like they don't want to get into the
weeds on like some narrow slice of the
problem that's like or some stuff that's
even like I mean, I think our space is
actually not very narrow. Part of the
challenge of it is that there's so many
things going on in mobile in such a huge
service area and like you know, could
you attempt to build all this stuff that
we built? Like, yeah, you could with
enough effort you could and you probably
you probably be easier the second time
around cuz you could just look at what
we did in a lot of cases. Probably true
for, you know, RevenueCat as well.
There's like if you wanted to build
something that was like RevenueCat, you
could just look at it and copy but
there's a lot of detail I'm sure there's
a thousand details that were Yeah, that
that LLMs actually aren't great at
understanding, right? Necessarily,
right?
Yeah, and so a lot of I think a lot of
these people like just want to offload
things to pieces that they kind of know
work and are well more than like try to
compete with them
necessarily. We'll see though how things
play out. A developer friend I've worked
with for for years who who was also a
very kind of snooty native developer for
a long time was telling me how much he
enjoys working with LLMs and React
Native
because it closes the loop as well
because the LLM can actually render it,
test it, and close the loop on that.
Have you been seeing that as a trend as
well of like it just getting better and
better at being so quick? It like you
were saying, you don't want to have to
compile an app, wait
5 minutes to then test the code. Yeah,
even like using Cursor or using ChatGPT
alongside Xcode is just like a it's a
substandard experience to using one of
these five coding tools for that reason,
right? Like the LLM can actually run the
code which is a huge advantage.
One thing I've heard is that one of the
one of the reasons that
these LLMs are quite good at writing
code compared to a lot of other things
is because
they could like generate output and then
run the code and tell if it like worked.
And so they could a lot easier to like
train on that versus like is this a good
poem?
When I ask it to come up with company
strategy, it has no way to RL that back
in for example. But then there's also
this is maybe not quite what you're
talking about but like that's sort of
what you're talking about but
a zoomed-out version to some extent
where I was I used to work with a guy
who was like a really good
designer/Swift
engineer.
And he had started a new startup that
was like a consumer product and they had
built it in Swift for all the reasons
that, you know,
people who
you know, oh, we have to get every
interaction perfect. It's about, you
know, we're we're consumer of things, so
every little detail matters, blah, blah,
And they'd been in this spot where they
had something that people liked, but it
just wasn't like quite at that point
where it was like could raise like a
series B or just was like really off to
the races. And so they needed to kind of
work on it, but also was like, you know,
had some network effects. So they were
kind of like, "Well, we kind of need to
be on Android and web, but we also kind
of need to be changing this product. And
so like are we going to like freeze
everything and go build an Android
version, but then we're going to be
stuck with two versions of the code and
we're never going to be able to move
forward. And like it also even if we
were just sticking with iOS, like it
takes us a long time to make even one
new screen or
whatever. And so his, you know, he's
working on a new thing now and it's he's
basically just sort of like, yeah, I'm
like you just using Expo for it. The
technology has come to the point where
I've been able to make
the things that I need to do and I can
just tell so much more quickly whether I
like something or not. And I can drop
down into Swift when I need to, but I
actually haven't really needed to at all
yet. And so I think that like a lot of
people are kind of like learning
all their lessons about iteration the
hard way or it's like you a lot of times
you end up in this middle ground where
you're like, this is kind of good, but
it's not exactly what I want. And like
if you if you can't like it just you
have to really know what you want, I
think when you're if if it's to make it
worth it. Even if there is some relative
difficulty working with the tools, like
they can easily be wiped out by like a
small increase in iteration speed,
right? Yeah, Jacob and I were talking
about this before we got on. Craigslist,
I went and looked it up on the App Store
cuz I I haven't used Craigslist in
years. Actually, I hadn't even
downloaded the app, surprisingly. But
it's got like 450,000 reviews and an
average of 4.8 stars. And you know, my
reflection upon seeing that was that
React Native app, by the way, or Expo
Expo driven React Native app, by the
way, which Charlie and I were talking on
the call like my long story too much
detail but my wife worked there back in
2016-17 and this was like something I
went in and talked to them about to help
them. I'm probably breaking an NDA, I
don't care. And apparently like this was
I said, "Oh, you should check out Expo."
And apparently it was one of the first
like big companies or something or like
sort of like shocking logos that you saw
Charlie, which is pretty funny. They
reached out to us and we're sort of
like, "Hey, we're thinking about using
you for a we didn't have any I think the
biggest thing though with Expo at that
point was like Urban Dictionary's.
That's a kind of a big I mean That's
cool. You're starting out the starting
out the fringes of brand but like uh you
know, that's a big step up. Well, yeah,
yeah, I was just going to say upon
seeing that it it really struck me that
people review and they care about and
they rate the the outcome. Is
Craigslist helping me do what I set out
to achieve? They're not rating every
little interaction that you think needs
to be perfect. And I mean just looking
at the screenshots, you can tell that
Craigslist app is as Craigslist website
is. So, it's not this like incredibly
polished like perfect experience.
Yeah, you might you might be developing
what's the actual constraining factor
here like limiting factor. Maybe it's
not Expo's polish or React Native's
polish but maybe maybe Craigslist's
design.
Right, totally. But but the point being
that people love the app, you know, 4.8
stars, 450,000
reviews. There's a lot of native apps
out there that that that aren't anywhere
close to that, right? One is it that the
biggest user of React Native inside of
Meta, I think is actually the
Marketplace thing which gets you like a
billion people using it every day. And
so like both I guess Craigslist and also
the thing that sort of replaced
Craigslist for a lot of us are both and
I think Marketplace is actually quite
nice.
I was telling David before this it's my
favorite social network. I just love to
go on there and browse and just it's
entertaining. The algo is not
aggressively trying to get my attention.
It's awesome. Uh and it's very real. But
then the other thing that reminded me of
was like one of the things that's driven
me crazy for years and part of the
reason I work on this is that like when
I look around and look Look how people I
know and and even myself use software.
I'm mostly on my mobile device. I'm
somebody who's like my job is to sit at
a computer all day. Like so I'm
definitely not like anti-computer, but
like most people
don't have
jobs where they sit in front of a
computer all day. I think it's become
much much less normal for like people
who don't have computer jobs or
enthusiasts to have a PC that they use
regularly. But if you think about like
what do developers work on? It's kind of
like most people out there like web
developers who make websites for people
sitting at their computer. And like
whereas in the way we're using software
is like most people are just like using
the app on their phone for whatever. And
like this is getting more and more true
where it used to be like, you know, I
wouldn't write important emails on my
phone. I would sit down on my And now
like most of the important emails I
write I write from my phone. And I would
even say to people like, "Well,
probably, you know, early days of Expo
at some days I would point this out and
I'd be like, you know, it's not like
we're going to, you know, first-person
shooter video games and video editing
and stuff like that. That's probably,
you know, not going to move to mobile."
But now like TikTok probably has more
minutes of video edited per day than the
sum of you know, Final Cut and Premiere
or whatever. And then, you know, I'm
sure that the the sum total of minutes
played on like, you know, first-person
shooters on Android devices is bigger
than PCs these days and whatnot. Yeah.
How many people are playing
Counter-Strike sitting down and playing
Counter-Strike anymore, you know? All
these things I was like, "Oh, well, I
don't know if this will move over." They
all basically have. And so like part of
what I just want to solve with this
like, how do you make it so that like
it's easy enough to work on mobile stuff
so that we can line up the like
developer effort and energy with like
how people are actually using software
in the world because we should like I
remember I was at a in Miami and I was
sitting next to somebody who was telling
me they were working on uh
some one of these like weed buying
startups or whatever. And they were they
told me they had a they were working on
a 20-person developer team.
And it was like, "Oh, yeah, there's
like,
you know, I think we have me and
sometimes this other person with like
half of their time helps me on the app
and we're using, you know, React Native
for it. And then I was like, "Oh, okay."
Like and he was like like and he was
like, "Yeah, pretty much everybody else
works on the website." And I was like,
"Well, oh, so like the app must be some
sort of like add-on here or, you know,
not that important to your" And he was
like, "No, no, 95% of our sales are
through the app." But for whatever
reason like, you know, you can hire web
developers and so they just like that's,
you know, they had all these people
working on the website and they're just
like I think a lot of the industry is in
the state where it's like it's so much
easier to write stuff and deploy stuff
on the web and there's just such a a
better development experience in history
that we end up like gravitating that
direction. These constraints like kind
of echo and like they create like some
sort of imbalances like, you know,
accidentally. But I do think that some
of these things are changing and getting
a bit easier to deal with and and
whatnot. And you know, some of the ways
that some policies changing based on
some of these lawsuits and whatnot. I
think it's going to make
potentially a distribution easier in
some ways. I think I only expect it to
get more liberalized, right? Like I
don't expect Apple to get more, you
know, I think the trend was likely to
continue with and without lawsuits. I
think there'll just be I think it's kind
of the way I think of it sort of like,
you know, when Uber first launched I
think it was probably technically
illegal in a lot of places, but it's
just like at the end of the day like if
something is really good where it's like
it just gets if If the people demand it,
it will happen.
like eventually will sort of the the
floodgates will kind of the dam will
leak or burst or something. Well, I
think that's a a great topic to wrap up
on, you know, with the increase in
tooling, with AI, with everything that's
going on in the industry. It is just
faster and easier to build software that
helps people and that's really cool and
it's exciting to be a part of it.
Anything else you wanted to share as we
were wrapping up? No, I feel like I got
to shill our product for an hour. So,
that's that's all right. As you say, you
could go to you could go to Expo's
website, but honestly people will
probably just find you via Bolt, you
know, like it'll just be LLMs will tell
you to go there. But no, I think it's
really cool what you guys are building.
I think it's like a
I don't know, you get me excited that,
you You we're still early days on this
like transition to mobile and like in
fact like maybe much like e-com and
Shopify, you know, opened up e-com for a
lot of people. I still think like mobile
development and development in general
is now just finally getting opened up
and Expo plays a big part of that. It's
just really cool. So, Yeah, thanks for
the work you're doing. All right, thanks
Charlie. All right, have a great day
David. Talk to you later Jacob.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.